good evening here's what's happening the
report on the space shuttle disaster is
now in President Reagan's hands and the
public will get a look at it on Monday
tonight CNN's John Hollman reports some
hard-fought battles among members of the
investigative commission that wrote the
report one member was harshly critical
of NASA and therein lies the tale that
John hullman unfolds now from
Washington commission member Richard
feineman charged that NASA had virtually
ignored the principles of physics and
good scientific practice in designing
testing and building the space shuttle
the Nobel prize winning physicist wrote
a section of the final report known as
chapter F commission sources say
chairman William Rogers read the chapter
and was Furious he called pinan to
Washington Wednesday and urged him to
tone down his criticism of NASA because
chapter F threatened to destroy public
confidence in the space agency binan
returned to his home in California and
began his rewrite but then changed his
mind sources close to the scientists say
he felt his ethics were being being
compromised he sent a message to Rogers
threatening to resign from the
commission and demanding his name be
taken off the final report if his
chapter was not included in its entirety
after a day of tense negotiation Fineman
agreed to stay on the commission and
sign the final document but the result
of all this is that President Reagan
will not read Dr Fan's criticism this
weekend at Camp David his chapter will
be printed and released as part of the
lengthy appendix to the report at the
White House a senior Administration
official says there's still no consensus
on a fourth shuttle Orbiter but CNN has
learned the president does support the
plan to replace Challenger the senior
officials says if the fourth Orbiter is
approved the president will ask Congress
to appropriate money to build it rather
than take money from current NASA
programs John hollan CNN
Washington the members one promises to
be somewhat more harsh in its evaluation
of the space agency than the general
commission report being made public
today sources close to the panel say the
Nobel physicist Richard finman had
concluded that the chances of a
catastrophic shuttle accident were far
greater than NASA had predicted before
the Challenger disaster did happen Dr
fman you may remember was one of the
more skeptical members of the Rogers
commission he' asked some of the tougher
questions of the NASA Witnesses in fact
he had threatened not to sign the final
report out today because it was he
thought not Tough Enough later however
Professor pman reached an agreement with
William Rogers on the report's language
and he signed the report being made
public today
good
morning with us now for a newsmaker
interview as a key member of the
presidential commission he is Richard
feineman the Nobel prize winning
physicist from the California Institute
of Technology welcome sir was this an
accident that did not have to happen yes
yes it was it was uh an
accident that had many many warnings
that there was something wrong and that
it might sooner or later go off and uh
the warnings were dis disregarded
disregarded out of incompetence out of a
faulty system out of bad judgment out of
for what reason I had some difficulty
with that I kind of imagine that
something like a child that runs in the
in the road and the parent is very
upset and says it's very dangerous and
the child comes back and says but
nothing happen and he runs out in the
road again several times and parent
keeps saying it's dangerous and nothing
happens if the child's view that nothing
happened is a clue that there was
nothing going to happen then that's
going to be an accident you could hear
Brak squealing a couple of times that's
leakage and the gas is going through the
Rings and so forth but again and again I
saw in looking through this statements
this new flight is within our database
which just means nothing happened before
it's about the same as we did before so
it can't be unsafe because it was okay
last time and that is a kind of childish
attitude that uh the mother correspond
to the engineers here right and the
management corresponding to the children
and that's the way I look at it and I
don't know what you would say sooner or
later the child gets run over is it an
accident no it's not an accident and yet
your commission and we just heard uh
chairman Rogers your chairman say we
should we're not here to blame anybody
why not why not why is somebody not
blamed
I don't know how to assign blame and
whether it does any good the question is
how do we educate the child uh the
question is you could say you blame the
child for being a little foolish but
it's very difficult I tried to figure
out why they have this this attitude and
why they weren't paying attention I've
tried various theories and I really
don't know the ultimate cause what's
your theory well one of the there's two
the people a lot of people say to me
that there's some kind of of an idea in
management that the incompetence reaches
its level or whatever but I had another
idea which I don't know whether it's
right and that is that in the beginning
all kinds of exaggerations were made
about what this thing can do it can fly
60 flights it will only cost so much
it'll be recoverable and there'll be no
real problems the engineers at the
bottom has probably scream this is my
imagination they're screaming up no no
it can't be this way it can't be this
way we can only go 10 flights we haven't
got enough equipment to train that many
crews a year so forth and so on and the
people at the top were talking to
Congress don't want to hear this and so
they discourage information from moving
up you see it was just after they were
so successful with Apollo and in that
case they were doing a project with just
a little bit harder than they could do
just a little bit harder so they could
do it and it would solve one problem
this is my imag I'm imagine I was
somebody would say we can how we going
to make a space finally they got a
solution to that they get excited and
tell the others fell are working on some
other problem gets a solution to his
problem and there's a lot of
intercommunication because there's
excitement and motivation but when the
people which is not always necessarily a
bad thing right no not at all it's what
makes it Go and that's why it worked
okay with the
Apollo but then when they had this other
project which is so to speak impossible
from an engineering point of view it's
unrealistic they don't want to hear what
happens it does goes up and each level
in a bureaucracy kind of understands
what it's supposed to do keep it from
the other guys they don't have to hear
it they don't want to hear it they don't
want to hear it because it would be
uncomfortable to be going and saying
we're going to do 60 flights a year when
just that morning they were told that
it's
impossible that's with Theory now I as
you know you're a professor of physics
and not of management and human
relations and so it's very likely not
right but you asked me for my theory at
the one of the hearings by in fact I
think it was the first public hearing
you took a glass of water and dropped a
piece of uh Rubber seal into a glass of
water and made the demonstration that
cold weather is not necessarily a good
thing for a Rubber seal have you proven
was your theory in the glass been proven
correct do you think that's really what
caused the seal to go bad it was too
cold that's one of the one of the
possibilities uh certainly was one of
the
possibilities it's definite that when
the temperature is reduced on this the
seals the way they were being
used in that device in the shuttle
temperature has a very bad effect what
caused a certain amount of trouble is
that o o-ring seals is used auto in
automobiles and so on are in a position
where the space is constant that the the
space that they have to isn't move and
therefore resilience is not vital and
the temperature is not it's not
sensitive to temperature so everybody
thought seals are not sensitive to
temperature but the way this seal was
being used the space ing between the
Rings and so on would vibrate as the
thing blew up with the pressure and
would move and the ring has to follow
that and when it's cold it can't follow
that so that's definitely a possible
contributor but as we looked into this
thing we found so many other problems
associated with the seal design that
there was a kind of putty that could
have holes blown into it there was
problems about whether there were all
other kinds of difficulties I got you so
com we couldn't decide exactly what it
was and I wouldn't be able to say that
it was solely the temperature but that
certainly was a possibility how do you
feel about the job your commission did
generally I think we did a pretty good
job it turned out to be easier in some
respects than we could have imagined it
was easy to find out what happened I but
I was curious why did Chairman Rogers uh
say at the White House today that it
would turned out to be more difficult
than he thought it was going to be what
was he talking about well maybe we had
different
expectations it's strange because at the
very beginning of this commission
meeting I remember Mr Rogers saying well
of course we may never find out what
made the accident occur and that turned
out that's what I meant was easy I see
you know what happened and we know what
happened now the what was difficult and
I think maybe he's referring to this was
the discovery of these weaknesses inside
of NASA and their attitudes MH this kind
of illogic about safety and so forth
which was so extensive from an
organization which had such a reputation
in the country that it was hard for us
to find it out in a sort of emotional
way as to have to come around and say
that the wizard of ozs which everybody
respects has nothing behind it the New
York Times almost nothing almost okay
the New York Times reported this morning
that you had some you had a clash with
uh chairman Rogers over an appendix and
other and also U Elizabeth Brackett in
her report referred to that passing
what's that all about well that's
terribly exaggerated got into the news
somehow I have no control of news have
no experience
with uh at one point I had
written a document which was meant for
the other Commissioners I had
investigated a number of things and I
was just sending them a note telling
them what i' found and it wasn't written
for
publication uh then there was a
discussion the various commissioner
members who looked at it said it was
pretty good and we ought to just put it
in the report but it wasn't it was
written in a personal style it wasn't
proper for the rest of the report so
since we're going going have appendices
which have a lot of detail they said
let's put it in appendix and I'm very
happy with
that but because we had this habit of
modifying and and trying to keep things
short by cutting things down that were
repetitious and there were some things
in there that were also in the report it
started to modify this and I looked at
it and I thought it was nice the way I
wrote it you know so I asked that it be
put in the since it was in the appendix
and we weren't so worried about space
let's leave it in the appendix with any
modification at all and they said okay
but look at this sentence isn't written
very well and I agreed definitely it was
only a suggestion that I changed the
sentence and I changed it not because I
lost any ideas I had said the same idea
in a careful and much more quiet way
earlier on in a paragraph and there was
no need to repeat it it improved the
sentence it's just
typographical I also made another change
where I found a sentence had bad grammar
nobody knows about that one there's no
stink about that one so there's no stink
here there's no stink here at all no sir
there's no problem it so as far as
you're concerned you're this was a
unanimous report from the commission and
uh sir you didn't go away with any scars
and neither to Chairman Rog all right Dr
fman don't go away we'll be back thank
you Charlene NASA